A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, A-E FA391
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Downs, Wilbur G.
  - 1950, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 193 pages (Reel M Dow 1, Frame 544, Box 126)
    As Mexican public health initiatives remain pressed for funds, Dr. Downs continues to recommend either DDT residual spraying or anti-larval campaigns as a means of malaria control. It is Dr. Downs' goal to promote the sustainability of Mexican malaria control using Mexican money; and to avoid dependency on foreign funds. Dr. Downs emphasizes the importance of local support for malaria; continued attendance at training sessions instituted to educate Mexicans in the public health field; and the gradual accession of malaria programs by the state. He also comments upon the challenges that face effective public health campaigns given the limitations of the Mexican government. Scientific investigation at the experimental houses at Acatlipa continues. Research focuses on DDT analysis and, in particular, on the retention of DDT residue on adobe bricks. As for the insectary, there, Dr. Downs continues his work maintaining the mosquito colonies and carrying our experimental testing on different mosquito habits, mosquito species, and species of the malaria parasite. His field trips throughout Mexico lead to conclusions on the progress and/or success of state-wide malaria programs and also lead to conclusions on the prevalence of malaria in regions where children are examined for infection.
    Diaries; Arboviruses; DDT (Insecticide); Epidemiology; Entomology; Prevention and health; Public health; Malaria; Mexico
  - Index for 1951, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 7 pages (Reel M Dow 1, Frame 737, Box 126)
    Alphabetical Index by Individual: includes an "Index by week" at the end of the individual index.
    Alphabetical Index by Subject and Organization: headings include, "Medical Schools," "Health Units," "Insecticides," "Guerrero localities," "Requests for aid," and "Trips."
    Public health; Mexico; Prevention and health; Epidemiology; indexes (reference sources)
  - 1951, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 182 pages (Box 126, Reel M Dow 1, Frame 751)
    Quantitative and biological analysis of DDT and other insecticides continues, as Dr. Downs and the personnel of his office investigate the retention of DDT on adobe bricks, the decomposition of DDT in soil, and the repellent effects of DDT and insecticides in general. Dr. Downs visits the control houses at Acatlipa frequently to conduct such research. At the insectary, investigation focuses on the susceptibility of different anopheline species to contract varying strains of malaria. Both biological (e.g. mosquito age, breeding patterns) and environmental factors (e.g. temperature) are analyzed by Dr. Downs and his team to substantiate any correlation. Diary entries also recount the development and progress of anti-malaria programs by summarizing the status of training centers, scientific investigations, and malaria prevention throughout the country. Frequent field trips to towns and states outside of Mexico continue, and while on such visits Dr.Downs administers anti-malaria drugs and recommends an appropriate method of malaria prevention. Extensive data and observations on the state of malaria in Guerrero are included in this period. Office work mostly involves the logistics of transferring Dr.Down's office and personnel to a new Malaria Investigation Office, headed by the state; RF funding of the office terminates at the end of 1951.
    Epidemiology; Mexico; Prevention and health; Public health; Diaries
  - 1952, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 77 pages (Box 126, Reel M Dow 1, Frame 933)
    With the RF office in Mexico officially closed at the end of 1951, Dr. Downs' administrative duties are minimized; his efforts are focused upon transferring the Malaria Investigation Office to the Mexican government and continuing ongoing laboratory experiments with DDT and regional surveys of malaria infection rates. The capacity of the Mexican government to finance and provide adequate leadership for public health initiatives is a main concern of Dr. Downs as he makes arrangements to leave Mexico for Trinidad. Upon arriving in Port of Spain Dr. Downs commences the task of launching the Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory: a dually funded institution backed by the Rockefeller Foundation and the Trinidadian government. There, Dr. Downs' expertise is dedicated to establishing the laboratory; furnishing it with supplies and personnel; and laying the groundwork for scientific research. Investigation at the laboratory will center on identifying endemic viruses (e.g. dengue fever, meningitis, rabies, etc.) and isolating the vectors that transmit them (e.g. mosquitoes, rats, birds, swine, etc.)
    Trinidad; Rabies; Arboviruses; DDT (Insecticide); Epidemiology; Entomology; Dengue; Public health; Prevention and health; Diaries; Mexico; Malaria
  - 1952 December 29-1953 December 13, Rockefeller Foundation; Downs, Wilbur G.; 104 pages (Box 126, Reel M Dow 1, Frame 1,010)
    Logistical work in Port of Spain persists as Dr. Downs continues to establish the Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory: a dually funded institution backed by the Rockefeller Foundation and the Trinidadian government. As for the laboratories research, investigation focuses upon examining blood specimens in order to determine what virus agents are present; and, thus, conclude which viruses are responsible for the undiagnosed fevers present in Trinidadian clinics. Mouse and mosquito colonies are being established for use by the laboratory and other mammals and birds are being collected as well. All such specimens are to be tested in order to determine which vectors harbor which viral agents. Particular attention is paid to the mosquito colony and the overall composition of the forest mosquito population in Trinidad.
    DDT (Insecticide); Rabies; Arboviruses; Public health; Prevention and health; Malaria; Epidemiology; Entomology; Dengue; Trinidad; Diaries
  - 1953 December 14-1954 December, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 181 pages (Box 127, Reel M Dow 2, Frame 1)
    With the Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory in full operation, Dr. Downs and his team of laboratory technicians and scientists begin a country-wide campaign to collect blood specimens of animals and humans afflicted with undiagnosed fevers and encephalitis. Concentrating on medicaland not clinicalscience, Dr. Downs and his team inoculate animals with viral strains (obtained from infected persons) in hopes of identifying the viral agents causing the undiagnosed maladies. Given the ubiquity of encephalitis in this particular time period, Dr. Downs begins to suspect that the country may be on the verge of a Yellow Fever epidemic. By investigating the abnormal dying-off of indigenous monkeys and the loss of five human victims, Dr. Downs and his team successfully isolate strains of Yellow Fever and alert the Trinidadian authorities that it has reemerged. A government vaccination campaign is launched and other South and Central American authorities are warned as well. A conference in Washington is organized in order to address the threat of Yellow Fever in the Americas and in the United States. Dr. Downs is an attendee and speaker at the conference.
    Diaries; Yellow fever; Dengue; DDT (Insecticide); Arboviruses; Malaria; Epidemiology; Entomology; Trinidad; Rabies; Public health; Prevention and health
  - 1955, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 176 pages (Reel M Dow 2, Frame 200, Box 127)
    Dr. Downs and his personnel at the Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory continue to survey the distribution of viral agents and vectorsboth insect and mammalon the island of Trinidad. Human, animal, and mosquito blood specimens are collected in order to identify viral agents and mice are inoculated with the viral agents so that strains may be isolated. In order to acquire human blood specimens from patients with unidentified fevers, Dr. Downs begins to work part-time at the Sangre Grande clinic, exchanging his services as a practitioner for blood specimens. In this manner, a variety of viral strains are isolated including strains of the Ilheus, Dengue and Yellow Fever virus. Further analysis of Yellow Fever consists of a Yellow Fever Immunization Study and medical analysis of patients before and after receiving the Yellow Fever vaccination. All entomological, epidemiological, and laboratory activities from July to December are described in detail in a fortnightly report.
    Dengue; DDT (Insecticide); Flaviviruses; Diaries; Malaria; Entomology; Epidemiology; Trinidad; Yellow fever; Prevention and health; Public health
  - 1955 December 15-1956 December 31, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 253 pages (Box 127, Reel M Dow 2, Frame 376)
    Dr. Downs' diary entries take the form of monthly reports regarding the entomological, epidemiological, laboratory, and zoological activities of the Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory for this entire period. The reports include extensive data and observations on experiments, animals, and patients related to the isolation of viral agents, and discuss the progress of supplementary projects such as the establishment of an insectary and the collection of animal skins. Strains of mayaro, dengue, ilheus, yellow fever, St. Louis, and malaria are the primary viruses being isolated and studied at the TRVL. Surveys and preliminary data on Grenada and British Guiana are included as supplements to two of the monthly reports.
    Flaviviruses; Epidemiology; Prevention and health; Malaria; St. Louis encephalitis; Public health; Yellow fever; Trinidad; Diaries; Entomology; DDT (Insecticide); Dengue
  - 1960 February 12-May 16, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 54 pages (Box 127, Reel M Dow 2, Frame 629)
    On behalf of the Rockefeller Foundation, Dr. Downs visits various countries where there is RF involvement or where RF funds might be of use in the future. The diary entries comprise a travelogue of the cities, institutions, and laboratories that Dr. Down's visits and also include descriptions of the personnel he meets and their respective research. The countries included on Dr. Down's tour are Thailand, Great Britain, Singapore, Kenya, Jamaica and South Africa. As an expert of epidemiology and malaria with extensive experience in RF development programs, Dr. Down's main purpose is to assess the progress of existing programs; offer technical advice on scientific practices; and consult with colleagues on potential improvements of existing programs and future proposals.
    Diagnostic virology; Arboviruses; Epidemiology; Public health; Diaries
  - 1962, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 164 pages (Box 127, Reel M Dow 2, Frame 683)
    On behalf of the Rockefeller Foundation, Dr. Downs visits various countries where there is RF involvement; where there is the potential for RF involvement; and/ or where there is epidemiological research relevant to Dr. Down's expertise being conducted. The diary entries comprise a travelogue of the cities, institutions, and laboratories that Dr. Downs surveys and also include descriptions of the personnel he meets as well as their respective research. The countries included on Dr. Down's tour are Egypt, India, Ceylon, Singapore, Malaya, Thailand, Philippines, Great Britain, Nigeria, Italy and Jamaica. While in Jamaica, Dr. Downs is involved in discussions regarding the future of the Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory. The plan is to transfer the laboratory, personnel included, to the University College of the West Indies. Additionally, while in Jamaica, an epidemic of Eastern Equine Encephalitis unfolds. Dr. Downs describes this event in detail in the entries spanning his visit.
    Epidemiology; Public health; Diaries; Arboviruses; Diagnostic virology; University College of the West Indies (Mona, Jamaica); Yale Arborvirus Research Unit
  - 1963, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 200 pages (Reel M Dow 2, Frame 847, Box 127)
    Scope and Contets note
    Now assigned to the RF office in New York, Dr. Downs apportions his time between administrative duties related to the public health activities at the RF and the RF virus laboratory. Entries describe scientific reports that Dr. Downs submits; epidemiological conferences attended; personnel with whom he has correspondence; and any institutionsboth private and publicthat he or the RF collaborates with on matters pertaining to public health. During this time period, many of Dr. Downs' entries are written from the Yale School of Epidemiology and Public Health: a joint establishment of Yale University and the RF. Trips include official visits to the RF programs located in Cali, Colombia, Port of Spain, Trinidad and Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. Entries record the status and progress of the aforementioned programs.
    Arboviruses; Diagnostic virology; Epidemiology; Diaries; Public health; Yale Arborvirus Research Unit
  - 1964, Rockefeller Foundation; Downs, Wilbur G.; 74 pages (Reel M Dow 2, Frame 1,047, Box 127)
    Apportioning time between the RF office in New York and the Yale office in New Haven, Dr. Downs tends to administrative duties pertaining to the creation of the virus laboratory at the Yale School of Epidemiology and Public Health. Included in the entries is a description of the agreement between Yale University and the Rockefeller Foundation regarding the establishment on the laboratory. All other entries include records of interviews and meetings; summaries of conferences and discussions had with colleagues in the field; and notes on research being conducted at the Yale virus laboratory. Entries describing Dr. Downs' travels to India, Thailand, Australia, Egypt, the Philippines, Taiwan, and Japan are also included and summarize the status and progress of epidemiologically related research, programs, and institutions abroad.
    Arboviruses; Diaries; Diagnostic virology; Epidemiology; Public health; Yale Arborvirus Research Unit
  - 1965, Rockefeller Foundation; Downs, Wilbur G.; 106 pages (Reel M Dow 3, Frame 1, Box 128)
    Dr. Downs conducts a number of medical, specifically epidemiological, surveysregarding the progress of public health initiatives and/or researchin Venezuela, Colombia, Brazil, Barbados, Trinidad, Nigeria, India, Hawaii, and India. While not on trips outside of the country, Dr. Downs dedicates his time to activities at the Yale Arbovirus Research Unit and at the RF New York office. In one correspondence to New York, Dr. Downs indicates that he has become the chairman of the Commission on Malaria, Armed Forces Epidemiological Board.
    Public health; Diaries; Arboviruses; Diagnostic virology; Epidemiology; American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene
  - 1966, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 26 pages (Box 128, Reel M Dow 3, Frame 109)
    While on extended trips to Colombia and Nigeria, Dr. Down's surveys the status and progress of public health and specifically, evaluates the progress and future of RF involvement in both countries. Epidemiological research at laboratories and public health institutions are also surveyed and Dr. Down's discusses relevant investigations in the diary entries. After returning to the US, Dr. Downs reports to San Juan, Puerto Rico for the annual meeting of the American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. Diary entries during his stay in San Juan address relevant public health issues and epidemiological research.
    Public health; Diaries; Epidemiology; Arboviruses
  - 1967, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 46 pages (Reel M Dow 3, Frame 135, Box 128)
    Scope and Contetns note
    Dr. Downs reviews public health programs and the progress of epidemiological research in Colombia, Venezuela, Brazil, Trinidad, Guyana, Suriname, French Guiana, and Nigeria. While the surveys of Guyana, Suriname and French Guiana address the overall status of national public health programs, the reports on Colombia, Venezuela, and Trinidad, instead, provide details concerning viral research and the growth of arbovirus laboratory programs. The field trip to Nigeria exclusively addresses social, political, technical, and business issues of concern to Nigeria; details of research and programs are not mentioned. Medical cooperation between Japan and the USA is discussed whilst Dr. Downs is in attendance at the U.S.-Japan Cooperative Medical Science Program, Working Conference on Small Pox.
    Diagnostic virology; Arboviruses; Diaries; Public health; Epidemiology
  - 1968, Rockefeller Foundation; Downs, Wilbur G.; 79 pages (Reel M Dow 3, Frame 181, Box 128)
    Between January and April of 1968, Dr. Downs travels to Ibadan, Nigeria; Kampala-Entebbe, Uganda; Tokyo, Japan; Taiwan; Bangkok, Thailand; Calcutta, Vellore and Poona, India; Pakistan; Jamaica; and Port of Spain, Trinidad on behalf of the Rockefeller Foundation. Country visits include meetings with RF fellowship applicants; tours of virus laboratories and other public health institutions; and meetings with professional personnel. When relevant, Dr. Downs' entries detail the status and progress of the epidemiological and university development programs that are of interest to the RF. On his trip to Jamaica, Dr. Downs attends the Meeting of Standing Advisory Committee for Medical Research in the British Caribbean. Details of the meeting are discussed in corresponding entries.
    Diaries; Public health; Epidemiology; Diagnostic virology; Arboviruses
  - 1969, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 9 pages (Reel M Dow 3, Frame 260, Box 128)
    Entries for this year describe three conventions that Dr. Downs attends. The first,"Working Conference on Viral Vaccines with Special Emphasis on Japanese Encephalitis," is held in Washington D.C; the second, "Conference on East Coast Fever and Trypanosomiasis," is held at the Bellagio Conference Center in Italy; and the third "AFEB Commission on Malaria," is held at the Walter Reed Army Institute of Research in Washington D.C.
    Epidemiology; Public health; Diagnostic virology; Arboviruses; Diaries; Walter Reed Army Institute of Research
  - 1970, Rockefeller Foundation; Downs, Wilbur G.; 57 pages (Reel M Dow 3, Frame 269, Box 128)
    Entries include descriptions of Dr. Downs' visits to international virus laboratories; details on working conferences that he attended in Tokyo, Japan through the Japan-U.S. cooperative Medical Science Program; details on conferences he attended that were hosted by the Armed Forces Epidemiological Board; and notes on the Annual Meeting of the American Society of Tropical Medicine in San Francisco. The following countries, and their respective programs, were visited by Dr. Downs: Trinidad (Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory), Suriname, French Guiana (Institut Pasteur), Brazil (Belem Virus Laboratory), Colombia (University of Valle), and Venezuela (Instituto Venozolano de Investigations Cientificas).
    Diaries; Epidemiology; Arboviruses; Diagnostic virology; Public health; Yale Arborvirus Research Unit
  - 1971, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 63 pages (Box 128, Reel M Dow 3, Frame 326)
    Entries for this year include descriptions of Dr.Downs' administrative work at the Yale Arbovirus Research Institute; a series of lectures he gave at the Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene and Public Health; visits to virus laboratoriesboth with and without RF fundingin Senegal (Institut Pasteur Dakar), Nigeria, Uganda, Ghana, and Colombia; and a series of meetings that Dr.Downs attended in East Africa, Trinidad, and Barbados. Entries from New Haven include a draft of the mission statement of the Yale School of Public Health.
    Diaries; Epidemiology; Public health; Diagnostic virology; Arboviruses; Yale Arborvirus Research Unit
- Dyer, Brian R.
  - 1938-1944 (Box 129)
  - 1946-1950 (Box 129)
- Elmendorf, John E.
  - 1947-1950, 1952 (Box 129)
- Embree, Edwin R.
  Edwin Rogers Embree was an early voice championing the Rockefeller Foundation's (RF) expansion into the humanities and social sciences.
  Born in Osceola, Nebraska in 1883, Embree moved with his family to the racially integrated town of Berea, Kentucky in 1891. His formative childhood years in Berea and his family's abolitionist history shaped his lifelong commitment to racial equality.
  Embree received his B.A. from Yale University in 1906. He spent a year in New York City as a reporter for the New York Sun before returning to New Haven in 1907. He spent the following decade working at Yale first as assistant editor of the Yale Alumni Weekly and then in several university administrative positions, while also earning an M.A. degree from the university in 1914. Embree's administrative work at Yale brought him to the attention of the Rockefeller Foundation, and in 1917 he was appointed secretary of the RF under president George E. Vincent.
  When Embree joined the RF, the Foundation's efforts were focused primarily on medicine and public health projects. Embree advocated for expanding their work into the humanities and social sciences. In a rousing 1924 address to RF Trustees and the General Education Board, he asked, "Of what good is it to keep people alive and healthy if their lives are not to be touched increasingly with something of beauty?" His speech received a lukewarm response from the Trustees, however. Embree instead channeled his efforts into directing the newly formed Division of Studies (DS), which was created in 1924 to administer all Foundation work in areas outside of medicine and public health. When the DS was eliminated in 1927, Embree went on to serve briefly as the RF's vice president. His vision for a robust humanities and social sciences program would not be fully realized until after his departure from the RF in 1928. That same year, the Foundation reorganized and established a Division of Humanities and a Division of Social Sciences.
  Embree left the RF in 1928 to become president of the Julius Rosenwald Fund, which supported educational, public health, and welfare programs for African Americans. When the Fund closed after expending all of its funds in 1948, Embree went on to serve as president of the Liberian and Africa Foundations, collectively focused on improving health, education, and welfare in Africa.
  In addition to his long philanthropic career, Embree was a prolific author. He wrote numerous articles, essays, and several books including Brown America: The Story of a New Race (1931), Brown Americans: The Story of a Tenth of the Nation (1943), and Thirteen Against the Odds (1944).
  Edwin Rogers Embree died in New York City on February 21, 1950, at the age of 66.
  - 1917-1918, Rockefeller Foundation; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers) (Reel M Emb 1, Frame 1, Box 130)
    The diary is arranged by interview and visit. Edwin Embree is the secretary of the Rockefeller Foundation and has various interactions with researchers, staff and professionals in field of philanthropy.
    Includes various memoranda.
    United States; Playgrounds; Military training camps; Diaries
  - Y.W.C.A. Memorandum, 1917; Rockefeller Foundation; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Young Women's Christian Association; 21 pages
    United States; Charity organization
  - Memoranda, January 1918; Rockefeller Foundation; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers)
    Arranged by interview and visit, this diary documents the meetings and conferences Embree had with various professionals in the field of public health. The diary includes Family Journals No. 1-7.
    Hygiene; France; Public health; Military training camps; Tuberculosis; Sex instruction; Venereal diseases; United States
  - Memoranda, 1918-1919; Rockefeller Foundation; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers)